<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Edge of Uncertainty</title>
    <description>Reviews of Adventure Books
</description>
    <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 21:10:39 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 21:10:39 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aurora</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780316098106&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Aurora.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;Aurora&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science Fiction has long been the domain of “big idea” novels and &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt;, by Kim Stanley Robinson—an author well-known for “big idea” novels—is no exception. Robinson is famous for his explorations of ecological themes such as sustainability and the relationship between nature and culture. In &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt;, he takes us into space in order to show us a fundamental truth about life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since ancient times, we humans have dreamed of what lies beyond our home planet. Whether we were thinking of the Moon, Mars, or some place much more distant, we have imagined not only finding places which we could inhabit, but places which are already inhabited. In all of this thinking, we tend to at least partially divorce the travelers from their origins, imagining that if one world exists that supports life as we know it, there could be others. Robinson uses &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt; to challenge this notion. “…life is a planetary thing,” a character named Euan says. “It begins on a planet and is part of that planet….So it can only live there, because it evolved to live there. That’s its home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novel begins as the ship is decelerating. After close to 160 years, it is approaching its target, the Tau Ceti system, fourteen light years away from Earth. The ship itself is an ark, basically, carrying representative populations of people, plants, and animals from each of Earth’s biomes. The goal is to find a planet suitable for colonization and then colonize it, making a new home for the ship’s residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is focused on Freya, a girl of fourteen at the beginning, and her parents—Devi, her mother, and Badim, her father. Devi is the ship’s main engineer. Her knowledge of the ship and its systems and her knack for problem-solving have made her responsible for holding the ship together as the wear and tear of its journey takes its toll. She worries that Freya has not inherited her abilities and will not be able to step in when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And indeed, Freya does not possess the technical proclivities that have made her mother so indispensable. However, in her travels through the ship’s biomes, she discovers that her talents lie in a different direction altogether. Where Devi’s purpose was to keep the ship going, Freya’s purpose is to keep its people going. Just as Freya is the heart of the story, she is the heart of the ship as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robinson tells us this story through the use of a narrative device—most of the novel is told to us by the ship’s computer, its artificial intelligence. It’s an interesting conceit and as I read the book, I could see why Robinson chose to write it this way. There are portions of the story that could not have been narrated by a human character and would have been less interesting had they been told by a third-person narrator. But it’s more than that, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship begins its narration, its story, because Devi asks it to. At first, the story is halting and too focused on technical matters. Ship doesn’t know how to tell a story. It is just a computer, after all. But Devi pushes and Ship tries harder and slowly, over the course of the book, the form of the narrative begins to take shape. The computer is learning and, through the act of storytelling, it becomes almost human, a character with its own desires and motivations, its own personality. Through the act of storytelling, it becomes itself, just as we humans become our own selves through the stories we tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not call &lt;em&gt;Aurora&lt;/em&gt; a quick or easy read. It is deep and challenging and incredibly rewarding. It’s the kind of book that generates epiphany after epiphany as you think more and more about the characters and their predicaments. I ended it with an overwhelming sense of awe at the process of evolution and the fact that sentient life exists at all. It’s also the kind of book that I would like to come back to, as I am sure there are many things I did not catch the first time through.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/04/06/Aurora.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/04/06/Aurora.html</guid>
        
        <category>science</category>
        
        <category>fiction,</category>
        
        <category>evolution</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>March Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;March was a little light, as far as adventure books, go. Really light, in fact. I only have two. But they both look excellent. &lt;em&gt;The Gutsy Girl&lt;/em&gt; by Caroline Paul is a book I wish I’d had as a young soon-to-be adventurer. As for &lt;em&gt;Delilah Dirk and the King’s Shilling&lt;/em&gt;, I ran out and bought that one the day it came out. I’m a huge fan of the first book in Tony Cliff’s series, I’m excited to read the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781632861238&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/March16/Gutsy_Girl.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Gutsy Girl: Escapades for your Life of Epic Adventure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Caroline Paul, illustrated by Wendy MacNaughton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781632861238&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Gutsy-Girl-Escapades-Adventure/dp/1632861232&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/907966106&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25663599-the-gutsy-girl&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;n The Gutsy Girl, author Caroline Paul emboldens girls to seek out a life of exhilaration. Once a young scaredy-cat herself, Caroline decided that fear got in the way of the life she wanted–of excitement, confidence, self-reliance, friendship, and fun. She has since flown planes, rafted big rivers, climbed tall mountains, and fought fires as one of the first female firefighters in San Francisco. In The Gutsy Girl, she shares her greatest escapades as well as those of other girls and women from throughout history, and offers engaging activities such as confidence-building stances, creating a compass, positive self-talk, and using crickets to estimate outside temperatures. Each section includes a place for girls to “journal” their adventures, thus encouraging a new generation to develop a zest for challenges and a healthy relationship to risk. The Gutsy Girl is Lean In for young girls, a book about the glorious things that happen when you unshackle from fear and open up to exhilaration. Fully illustrated and enlivened throughout by bestselling illustrator Wendy MacNaughton’s whimsical pen-and-ink drawings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781626721555&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/March16/Delilah_Dirk_Kings_Shilling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Delilah Dirk and the King’s Shilling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Tony Cliff&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781626721555&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Delilah-Dirk-Kings-Shilling-Cliff/dp/1626721556&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/904082072&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18721479-delilah-dirk-and-the-king-s-shilling&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Globetrotting troublemaker Delilah Dirk and her loyal friend Selim are just minding their own business, peacefully raiding castles and and traipsing across enemy lines, when they attract the unwanted attention of the English Army. Before they know it, Delilah and Selim have gotten themselves accused of espionage against the British crown!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Delilah will do whatever it takes to clear her good name, be it sneaking, skirmishing, or even sword fighting… But can she bring herself to wear a pretty dress and have a nice cup of tea with her mother? Delilah Dirk may be defeated at last. By tulle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/04/05/March_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/04/05/March_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>February Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Really, all the books here stood out to me as books I’d love to read. Elizabeth Marshall Thomas’s memoir sounds fascinating. I still have my copy of her book &lt;em&gt;The Harmless People&lt;/em&gt; which I read in a previous life as an anthropology student. &lt;em&gt;The Boiling River&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Wild By Nature&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Walking the Nile&lt;/em&gt; sound like true, old school, amazing adventures. And the fiction, one for older audiences and one for younger, look like the kind of stories that sweep you in, hold on tight, and possibly break your heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781603586399&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/Dreaming_of_Lions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Dreaming of Lions: My Life in the Wild Places&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elizabeth Marshall Thomas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781603586399&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Dreaming-Lions-Life-Wild-Places/dp/1603586393&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/919859486&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26715483-dreaming-of-lions&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dreaming of Lions traces Thomas’s life from her earliest days, including when, as a young woman in the 1950s, she and her family packed up and left for the Kalahari Desert to study the Ju/Wa Bushmen. The world’s understanding of African tribal cultures has never been the same since. Nor has Thomas, as the experience taught her not only how to observe, but also how to navigate in male-dominated fields like anthropology and animal science and do what she cared about most: spending time with animals and people in wild places, and relishing the people and animals around her at home.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Readers join Thomas as she returns to Africa, after college and marriage, with her two young children, ending up in the turmoil leading to Idi Amin’s bloody coup. She invites us into her family life, her writing, and her fascination with animals―from elephants in Namibia, to dogs in her kitchen, or cougars outside her New England farmhouse. She also recounts her personal struggles, writing about her own life with the same kind of fierce honesty that she applies to the world around her, and delivering a memoir that not only shares tremendous insights, but also provides tremendous inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781501119477&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/Boiling_River.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Boiling River: Adventure and Discover in the Amazon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Andrés Ruzo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781501119477&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Boiling-River-Adventure-Discovery-Amazon/dp/1501119478&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905685900&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25205390-the-boiling-river&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When Andrés Ruzo was just a small boy in Peru, his grandfather told him the story of a mysterious legend: There is a river, deep in the Amazon, which boils as if a fire burns below it. Twelve years later, Ruzo—now a geoscientist—hears his aunt mention that she herself had visited this strange river.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Determined to discover if the boiling river is real, Ruzo sets out on a journey deep into the Amazon. What he finds astounds him: In this long, wide, and winding river, the waters run so hot that locals brew tea in them; small animals that fall in are instantly cooked. As he studies the river, Ruzo faces challenges more complex than he had ever imaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781250081971&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/Wild_by_Nature.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Wild by Nature: From Siberia to Australia, Three Years Alone in the Wilderness on Foot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Sarah Marquis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781250081971&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Wild-Nature-Siberia-Australia-Wilderness/dp/1250081971&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/929155308&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25663856-wild-by-nature&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In Wild by Nature, National Geographic Explorer Sarah Marquis takes you on the trail of her ten-thousand-mile solo hike across the remote Gobi desert from Siberia to Thailand, at which point she was transported by boat to complete the hike at her favorite tree in Australia.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Against nearly insurmountable odds and relying on hunting and her own wits, Sarah Marquis survived the Mafia, drug dealers, thieves on horseback who harassed her tent every night for weeks, temperatures from subzero to scorching, life-threatening wildlife, a dengue fever delirium in the Laos jungle, tropic ringworm in northern Thailand, dehydration, and a life-threatening abscess.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This is an incredible story of adventure, human ingenuity, persistence, and resilience that shows firsthand what it is to adventure as a woman in the most dangerous of circumstance, what it is to be truly alone in the wild, and why someone would challenge themselves with an expedition others would call crazy. For Marquis, her story is about freedom, being alive and wild by nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780812997170&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/High_Mountains_of_Portugal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The High Mountains of Portugal: A Novel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Yann Martel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780812997170&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/High-Mountains-Portugal-Novel/dp/0812997174&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/911240030&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489094-the-high-mountains-of-portugal&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In Lisbon in 1904, a young man named Tomás discovers an old journal. It hints at the existence of an extraordinary artifact that—if he can find it—would redefine history. Traveling in one of Europe’s earliest automobiles, he sets out in search of this strange treasure.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thirty-five years later, a Portuguese pathologist devoted to the murder mysteries of Agatha Christie finds himself at the center of a mystery of his own and drawn into the consequences of Tomás’s quest.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fifty years on, a Canadian senator takes refuge in his ancestral village in northern Portugal, grieving the loss of his beloved wife. But he arrives with an unusual companion: a chimpanzee. And there the century-old quest will come to an unexpected conclusion.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The High Mountains of Portugal—part quest, part ghost story, part contemporary fable—offers a haunting exploration of great love and great loss. Filled with tenderness, humor, and endless surprise, it takes the reader on a road trip through Portugal in the last century—and through the human soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780802124494&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/Walking_the_Nile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Walking the Nile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Levison Wood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780802124494&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Walking-Nile-Levison-Wood/dp/0802124496&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/933780718&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24215252-walking-the-nile&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Nile, one of the world’s great rivers, has long been an object of fascination and obsession. From Alexander the Great and Nero, to Victorian adventurers David Livingstone, John Hanning Speke, and Henry Morton Stanley, the river has seduced men and led them into wild adventures. English writer, photographer, and explorer Levison Wood is just the latest. His Walking the Nile is a captivating account of a remarkable and unparalleled Nile journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780062377012&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/February16/Pax.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Sara Pennypacker, illustrated by Jon Klassen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780062377012&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Pax-Sara-Pennypacker/dp/0062377019&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/910530646&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22098550-pax&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pax and Peter have been inseparable ever since Peter rescued him as a kit. But one day, the unimaginable happens: Peter’s dad enlists in the military and makes him return the fox to the wild.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
At his grandfather’s house, three hundred miles away from home, Peter knows he isn’t where he should be—with Pax. He strikes out on his own despite the encroaching war, spurred by love, loyalty, and grief, to be reunited with his fox.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Meanwhile Pax, steadfastly waiting for his boy, embarks on adventures and discoveries of his own. . . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/03/14/Feb_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/03/14/Feb_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Odyssey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780763642686&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Odyssey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;The Odyssey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I had to read Christa Wolf’s &lt;em&gt;Cassandra&lt;/em&gt; in college, I’ve been fascinated with the Trojan War and Homer’s &lt;em&gt;Iliad&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve read all sorts of books that have to do with the Trojan War, from the &lt;em&gt;Iliad&lt;/em&gt; itself to Margaret George’s &lt;em&gt;Helen of Troy&lt;/em&gt; to Madeline Miller’s &lt;em&gt;The Song of Achilles&lt;/em&gt;. And there are many more that I still want to read. But, despite all of that, I have never felt the same level of fascination for Homer’s &lt;em&gt;Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, though, I decided to tackle it. I wanted to read it and I hoped to find that I liked it, at least. I do love a good adventure and &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; is pretty much the quintessential adventure story. The problem was, I’d never had much sympathy for Odysseus himself. For me his character had always been that of a mercenary, a man willing to do whatever he thought was necessary in support of whatever cause he deemed worthy. This was the man, after all, who came up with the Trojan Horse. He seemed smug and too clever, and the story of his fraught journey home did not appeal to me in the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I read it. And as I read it, I found myself questioning his every decision and move. Why wouldn’t he have told his men that there was wind in the bad and not riches? Why would he put everyone at risk and taunt Polyphemus the Cycolps? Wasn’t escaping enough? Why would he stay for a year with Circe? Why didn’t he try to escape from Calypso? I ended the book with possibly less sympathy for Odysseus than I had begun it with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I found Gareth Hinds’s graphic novel version and I couldn’t pass it up. The incredible image of Odysseus on his small raft on the front of the book with Poseidon looming large in the background was irresistible. And what I found inside was the story of the Odyssey through Hinds’s perspective. This is a story that he has loved for a long time and it shows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing the story through Hinds’s eyes, rather than my own, turned &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; into a different book for me. The story elements were familiar, but the emotions were not. Odysseus became a much deeper, much richer character than I had allowed myself to imagine. Yes, he still did all of those things that I had been critical of before, but now there were other things being brought to my attention—his misery, his tenderness, his pathos—things that I had not seen before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly taken with the way Hinds portrayed Odysseus’s relationship with Calypso. When I read that portion in Homer’s telling, it hadn’t occurred to me that Odysseus cared for Calypso at all. And yet, Hinds portrays the two of them as tender and even loving. Calypso has kept him, imprisoned him, in her island for seven years, but Odysseus does not seem angry. He is miserable, yes, and that misery is clear in Hinds’s illustrations, but he is not angry. And Calypso, yes, she is his jailer, but she is also his lover. Hinds shows us this clearly in his illustration of her watching Odysseus leave. She is standing on the beach, watching this man she wants to keep forever, the man she has offered to make immortal, as he sails away with her arms drawn across her body, her face full of sorrow and anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hinds’s graphic novel is full of moments like this. He draws attention to his characters’ emotions in a way that Homer did not. He shows us Penelope and Odysseus, far away from each other, yet mirroring each other’s misery on facing pages. We see the sorrow in Odysseus’s eyes when he finds his mother in the land of the dead, the surprise in seeing his son for the first time since leaving for Troy, and the depth of his heart in his reunion with Penelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hinds’s version has left me with a new appreciation for Odysseus and his hardships and I am truly grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/02/20/Odyssey.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/02/20/Odyssey.html</guid>
        
        <category>classics,</category>
        
        <category>Homer,</category>
        
        <category>history,</category>
        
        <category>ancient</category>
        
        <category>history</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>November-December-January Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have completely neglected this blog for the last few months. But now I’m back and I have a list of great adventure books that have come out over the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few biographies and books for younger readers on this list. A couple of them concerned forced adventures, journeys endured rather than enjoyed. This is an important aspect of adventure writing that often gets overlooked. Not all adventures are positive. &lt;em&gt;The Lightless Sky&lt;/em&gt; is about a boy who is a refugee from Afghanistan and his escape from that country and the danger that faced him there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also several books for younger readers. I’m particularly interested in &lt;em&gt;The Fox and the Star&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Anna and the Swallow Man&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;november&quot;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780226298375&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/theodore_roosevelt_in_the_field.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theodore Roosevelt in the Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Michael R. Canfield&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780226298375&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Theodore-Roosevelt-Field-Michael-Canfield/dp/022629837X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/907621821&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24693139-theodore-roosevelt-in-the-field&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Drawing extensively on Roosevelt’s field notebooks, diaries, and letters, Canfield takes readers into the field on adventures alongside him.  From Roosevelt’s early childhood observations of ants to his notes on ornithology as a teenager, Canfield shows how Roosevelt’s quest for knowledge coincided with his interest in the outdoors. We later travel to the Badlands, after the deaths of Roosevelt’s wife and mother, to understand his embrace of the rugged freedom of the ranch lifestyle and the Western wilderness. Finally, Canfield takes us to Africa and South America as we consider Roosevelt’s travels and writings after his presidency. Throughout, we see how the seemingly contradictory aspects of Roosevelt’s biography as a hunter and a naturalist are actually complementary traits of a man eager to directly understand and experience the environment around him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781501116292&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/438_days.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;438 Days: An Extraordinary True Story of Survival at Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Johnathan Franklin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781501116292&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/438-Days-Extraordinary-Story-Survival/dp/1501116290&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/915043925&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25111328-438-days&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On November 17, 2012, a pair of fishermen left the coast of Mexico for a weekend fishing trip in the open Pacific. That night, a violent storm ambushed them as they were fishing eighty miles offshore. As gale force winds and ten-foot waves pummeled their small, open boat from all sides and nearly capsized them, captain Salvador Alvarenga and his crewmate cut away a two-mile-long fishing line and began a desperate dash through crashing waves as they sought the safety of port.
Fourteen months later, on January 30, 2014, Alvarenga, now a hairy, wild-bearded and half-mad castaway, washed ashore on a nearly deserted island on the far side of the Pacific. He could barely speak and was unable to walk. He claimed to have drifted from Mexico, a journey of some seven thousand miles.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
“438 Days” is the first-ever account of one of the most amazing survival stories in modern times. Based on dozens of hours of exclusive interviews with Alvarenga, his colleagues, search-and-rescue officials, the remote islanders who found him, and the medical team that saved his life, “438 Days” is an unforgettable study of the resilience, will, ingenuity and determination required for one man to survive more than a year lost and adrift at sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781481422581&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/ticket_to_india.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ticket to India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by N. H. Senzai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781481422581&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Ticket-India-N-H-Senzai/dp/1481422588&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/911034505&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20487349-ticket-to-india&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A map, two train tickets, and a mission. These are things twelve-year-old Maya and her big sister Zara have when they set off on their own from Delhi to their grandmother’s childhood home of Aminpur, a small town in Northern India. Their goal is to find a chest of family treasures that their grandmother’s family left behind when they fled from India to Pakistan during the Great Partition. But soon the sisters become separated, and Maya is alone. Determined to find her grandmother’s lost chest, she continues her trip, on the way enlisting help from an orphan by named Jai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780143108672&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/the_fox_and_the_star.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Fox and the Star&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Coralie Bickford-Smith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780143108672&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Fox-Star-Coralie-Bickford-Smith/dp/0143108670&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908085077&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25387851-the-fox-and-the-star&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Fox and the Star is the story of a friendship between a lonely Fox and the Star who guides him through the frightfully dark forest. Illuminated by Star’s rays, Fox forages for food, runs with the rabbits, and dances in the rain—until Star suddenly goes out and life changes, leaving Fox huddling for warmth in the unfamiliar dark. To find his missing Star, Fox must embark on a wondrous journey beyond the world he knows—a journey lit by courage, newfound friends, and just maybe, a star-filled new sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781594203671&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/black_dragon_river.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Black Dragon River: A Journey Down the Amur River at the Borderlands of Empires&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Dominic Ziegler&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781594203671&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Black-Dragon-River-Journey-Borderlands/dp/1594203679&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/927297507&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24611853-black-dragon-river&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Black Dragon River is a personal journey down one of Asia’s great rivers that reveals the region’s essential history and culture. The world’s ninth largest river, the Amur serves as a large part of the border between Russia and China. As a crossroads for the great empires of Asia, this area offers journalist Dominic Ziegler a lens with which to examine the societies at Europe’s only borderland with east Asia. He follows a journey from the river’s top to bottom, and weaves the history, ecology and peoples to show a region obsessed with the past—and to show how this region holds a key to the complex and critical relationship between Russia and China today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780306822827&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/white_eskimo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;White Eskimo: Knud Rasmussen’s Fearless Journey into the Heart of the Arctic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Stephen R. Bown&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780306822827&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/White-Eskimo-Rasmussens-Fearless-Lawrence/dp/0306822822&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/910936242&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/21944911-white-eskimo&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Among the explorers made famous for revealing hitherto impenetrable cultures—T. E. Lawrence and Wilfred Thesiger in the Middle East, Richard Burton in Africa—Knud Rasmussen stands out not only for his physical bravery but also for the beauty of his writing. Part Danish, part Inuit, Rasmussen made a courageous three-year journey by dog sled from Greenland to Alaska to reveal the common origins of all circumpolar peoples. Lovers of Arctic adventure, exotic cultures, and timeless legend will relish this gripping tale by Stephen R. Bown, known as “Canada’s Simon Winchester.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781419707858&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/in_the_footsteps_of_crazy_horse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;In the Footsteps of Crazy Horse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Joseph Marshall III&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781419707858&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Footsteps-Crazy-Horse-Joseph-Marshall/dp/141970785X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/903284778&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24795887-in-the-footsteps-of-crazy-horse&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jimmy McClean is a Lakota boy—though you wouldn’t guess it by his name: his father is part white and part Lakota, and his mother is Lakota. When he embarks on a journey with his grandfather, Nyles High Eagle, he learns more and more about his Lakota heritage—in particular, the story of Crazy Horse, one of the most important figures in Lakota and American history. Drawing references and inspiration from the oral stories of the Lakota tradition, celebrated author Joseph Marshall III juxtaposes the contemporary story of Jimmy with an insider’s perspective on the life of Tasunke Witko, better known as Crazy Horse (c. 1840–1877). The book follows the heroic deeds of the Lakota leader who took up arms against the US federal government to fight against encroachments on the territories and way of life of the Lakota people, including leading a war party to victory at the Battle of the Little Bighorn. Along with Sitting Bull, Crazy Horse was the last of the Lakota to surrender his people to the US army. Through his grandfather’s tales about the famous warrior, Jimmy learns more about his Lakota heritage and, ultimately, himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;december&quot;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544445376&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/the_rosemary_spell.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Rosemary Spell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Virginia Zimmerman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544445376&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Rosemary-Spell-Virginia-Zimmerman/dp/0544445376&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/898052795&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719268-the-rosemary-spell&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Part mystery, part literary puzzle, part life-and-death quest, and chillingly magical, this novel has plenty of suspense for adventure fans and is a treat for readers who love books, words, and clues. Best friends Rosie and Adam find an old book with blank pages that fill with handwriting before their eyes. Something about this magical book has the power to make people vanish, even from memory. The power lies in a poem—a spell. When Adam’s older sister, Shelby, disappears, they struggle to retain their memories of her as they race against time to bring her back from the void, risking their own lives in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;january&quot;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780393239270&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/a_splendid_savage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A Splendid Savage: The Restless Live of Frederick Russell Burnham&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Steve Kemper&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780393239270&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Splendid-Savage-Restless-Frederick-Russell/dp/0393239276&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/909974262&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25622734-a-splendid-savage&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Frederick Russell Burnham’s (1861–1947) amazing story resembles a newsreel fused with a Saturday matinee thriller. One of the few people who could turn his garrulous friend Theodore Roosevelt into a listener, Burnham was once world-famous as “the American scout.” His expertise in woodcraft, learned from frontiersmen and Indians, helped inspire another friend, Robert Baden-Powell, to found the Boy Scouts. His adventures encompassed Apache wars and range feuds, booms and busts in mining camps around the globe, explorations in remote regions of Africa, and death-defying military feats that brought him renown and high honors. His skills led to his unusual appointment, as an American, to be Chief of Scouts for the British during the Boer War, where his daring exploits earned him the Distinguished Service Order from King Edward VII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780553513349&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/anna_and_the_swallow_man.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Anna and the Swallow Man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Gavriel Savit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780553513349&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Anna-Swallow-Man-Gavriel-Savit/dp/0553513346&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/891100702&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22453727-anna-and-the-swallow-man&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kraków, 1939. A million marching soldiers and a thousand barking dogs. This is no place to grow up. Anna Łania is just seven years old when the Germans take her father, a linguistics professor, during their purge of intellectuals in Poland. She’s alone.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And then Anna meets the Swallow Man. He is a mystery, strange and tall, a skilled deceiver with more than a little magic up his sleeve. And when the soldiers in the streets look at him, they see what he wants them to see.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Swallow Man is not Anna’s father—she knows that very well—but she also knows that, like her father, he’s in danger of being taken, and like her father, he has a gift for languages: Polish, Russian, German, Yiddish, even Bird. When he summons a bright, beautiful swallow down to his hand to stop her from crying, Anna is entranced. She follows him into the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385539289&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/the_road_to_little_dribbling.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Road To Little Dribbling: Adventures of an American in Britain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Bill Bryson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385539289&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Road-Little-Dribbling-Adventures-American/dp/0385539282&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908517220&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25489012-the-road-to-little-dribbling&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Following (but not too closely) a route he dubs the Bryson Line, from Bognor Regis in the south to Cape Wrath in the north, by way of places few travelers ever get to at all, Bryson rediscovers the wondrously beautiful, magnificently eccentric, endearingly singular country that he both celebrates and, when called for, twits. With his matchless instinct for the funniest and quirkiest and his unerring eye for the idiotic, the bewildering, the appealing, and the ridiculous, he offers acute and perceptive insights into all that is best and worst about Britain today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780062443878&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/the_lightless_sky.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Lightless Sky: A Twelve-Year-Old Refugee’s Harrowing Escape from Afghanistan and his Extraordinary Journey Across Half the World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Gulwali Passarlay&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780062443878&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Lightless-Sky-Twelve-Year-Old-Extraordinary/dp/0062443879&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/931476560&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26156481-the-lightless-sky&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2006, after his father was killed, Gulwali Passarlay was caught between the Taliban who wanted to recruit him, and the Americans who wanted to use him. To protect her son, Gulwali’s mother sent him away. The search for safety would lead the twelve-year-old across eight countries, from the mountains of eastern Afghanistan through Iran and Europe to Britain. Over the course of twelve harrowing months, Gulwali endured imprisonment, hunger, cruelty, brutality, loneliness, and terror—and nearly drowned crossing the Mediterranean Sea. Eventually granted asylum in England, Gulwali was sent to a good school, learned English, won a place at a top university, and was chosen to help carry the Olympic Torch in the 2012 London Games.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In The Lightless Sky, Gulwali recalls his remarkable experience and offers a firsthand look at one of the most pressing issues of our time: the modern refugee crisis—the worst displacement of millions of men, women, and children in generations. Few, like Gulwali, make it to a country that offers the chance of freedom and opportunity. A celebration of courage and determination, The Lightless Sky is a poignant account of an exceptional human being who is today an ardent advocate of democracy—and a reminder of our responsibilities to those caught in terrifying and often deadly circumstances beyond their control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780553520705&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/November15/the_goblins_puzzle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Goblin’s Puzzle: Being the Adventures of a Boy with No Name and Two Girls Called Alice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Andrew S. Chilton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780553520705&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Goblins-Puzzle-Adventures-Called/dp/0553520709&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/911004629&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22464760-the-goblin-s-puzzle&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;THE BOY is a nameless slave on a mission to uncover his true destiny.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
THE GOBLIN holds all the answers, but he’s too tricky to be trusted.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
PLAIN ALICE is a bookish peasant girl carried off by a confused dragon.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
And PRINCESS ALICE is the lucky girl who wasn’t kidnapped.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
All four are tangled up in a sinister plot to take over the kingdom, and together they must face kind monsters, a cruel magician, and dozens of deathly boring palace bureaucrats. They’re a ragtag bunch, but with strength, courage, and plenty of deductive reasoning, they just might outwit the villains and crack the goblin’s puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/02/06/Nov-Dec-Jan_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2016/02/06/Nov-Dec-Jan_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Thrilling Adventures of Lovelace and Babbage</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780307908278&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Lovelace_Babbage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;The Thrilling Adventures of Lovelace and Babbage&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Unless you pay close attention to either women’s history or the history of computers, you’ve probably never heard of Lady Ada Lovelace. And I can almost guarantee you’ve never heard of Charles Babbage. And yet their ideas are what made the world the live in today—a world in which we carry small computers in our pockets—possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Babbage was a nineteenth century mathematician. Actually, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Babbage&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; describes him as a polymath and I think that suits him quite well. He was one of those people who had fingers in many different pots. It seems, though, that what he really liked to do was solve problems, which is how he came up with the idea that would form the basis of the computer in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a solution to the problem of mistakes in the printed mathematical tables that were used at the time for things like navigation, engineering, and mathematics in general, Babbage developed the Difference Engine, basically a steam-powered machine designed to calculate the values of polynomial functions. From there he moved on to invent the Analytical Engine, a more complicated steam-powered machine designed to calculate all kinds of mathematical functions. It was to work using punch cards—an idea taken from the Jacquard Looms which used punch cards to encode the designs being woven into fabrics at the time—to program different mathematical calculations. Unfortunately, however, working models of his engines were not constructed during his lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ada Lovelace was a highly trained mathematician and a correspondent and friend of Charles Babbage. She was the daughter of the poet Lord Byron. Her mother, in an attempt to rout out any poetical instincts she might have, focused Lovelace’s education on mathematics from a very early age. And while Babbage may have designed a precursor to the modern computer, Lovelace wrote its first program. In the comments on a paper she translated from its original Italian, Ada Lovelace wrote an algorithm for calculating a sequence of Bernoulli numbers designed for Babbage’s Analytical Engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as history goes, this is where things generally stop. Babbage never built his engines—after his first attempt at building the Difference Engine failed, he had trouble getting more financing from the government—and Lovelace died of cancer at the age of 36. However, that didn’t stop Sydney Padua, an animator and visual effects artist, from imagining a more interesting and adventurous alternative history for the duo. And thank goodness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the introduction to the book, Ms. Padua writes that she hadn’t originally set out to draw a comic with an alternate-universe story about Lovelace and Babbage. She had done a web comic, just for fun, about the real Lovelace and Babbage, but since the ending to the real story is pretty sad, she added a little something extra. “I threw in a couple of drawings at the end, imagining for them another, better, more thrilling comic-book universe to live on in.” It had started as a joke, but the idea caught on and the more Ms. Padua researched her subjects, the more she fell in love with them and the more she felt compelled to make “an imaginary comic about an imaginary computer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book starts out with a retelling of the true story of Ada Lovelace and Charles Babbage. But then it quickly moves on to more imagined territory, sending us into a world in which the Analytical Engine is not only built, but being used to solve all sorts of problems. The duo challenge their engine to solve the country’s economic problems, and end up sending it running amok in the streets of London. The Queen of England wants to use it to fight crime. Charles Babbage declares a “War on Error” and ends up losing George Eliot’s book, which she and Lovelace must try to retrieve, given it’s her only copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ms. Padua’s drawings are fantastically steam-punk-esque, which is fitting given the fact that Babbage’s machines were steam-powered. The Analytical Engine is massive and Lovelace is frequently drawn strolling through the hallways between its stacks of gears in jodhpurs with a pipe and a frown. Ms. Padua portrays Babbage as a lovable idealist and inventor, not always cognizant of the consequences of loosing his ideas on the world. Lovelace, in contrast, is the workhorse of the pair, often cleaning up after Babbage’s messes and clearly enjoying her work inside the Engine itself, adjusting gears and whatnot, keeping the Engine in tiptop shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes the book truly magical however, are Ms. Padua’s footnotes and endnotes. While her comics are solidly constructed in the realm of fantasy, her footnotes and endnotes provide the historical bases for her flights of fancy. Clearly, she did a lot of research for this book. A whole lot. What she was able to dig up is amazing and her enthusiasm and love for these two rather eccentric characters shines through her writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was easy to fall in love with Lovelace and Babbage as Ms. Padua has portrayed them. I could see exactly what she meant when, in her introduction, she described Babbage as a “blend of Mr. Pickwick, Mr. Toad, Don Quixote, and Leonardo da Vinci” and how she wanted “alternately to shake [Lovelace], hug her, and throw her a parade.” Just dipping back into the book to write this review I found myself caught up once again in the stories and the characters that drive them. Long live Lovelace and Babbage!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/12/02/Lovelace_and_Babbage.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/12/02/Lovelace_and_Babbage.html</guid>
        
        <category>graphic</category>
        
        <category>novel,</category>
        
        <category>computers,</category>
        
        <category>history</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>October Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every month tons of new adventure books are published. And every month I realize that I will never be able to actually read them all. But I wanted to provide a list of a few adventure books that were published last month that look interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month I have some fiction! Well, three fiction books out of eight. But one of them is Volume Two of &lt;em&gt;Lumberjanes&lt;/em&gt; (I reviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html&quot;&gt;Volume 1&lt;/a&gt; in September) and that ought to count for something. More than something. I’ve already read it. It’s amazing. You should pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the other books that came out in October, I think I’m most excited about &lt;em&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Radiance&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/em&gt; has essays from some amazing writers I’ve read before (Paul Theroux, Maud Newton, Gary Schteyngart) and some that I’m sure are equally amazing, but that I just haven’t come across yet. &lt;em&gt;Radiance&lt;/em&gt; just looks incredible. It’s described as “a decopunk pulp SF alt-history space opera mystery” and I don’t even know what that means, but I want to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544569645&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Best_American_Travel_Writing_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edited by Andrew McCarthy and Jason Wilson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544569645&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Best-American-Travel-Writing-2015/dp/0544569644&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/922687833&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719269-the-best-american-travel-writing-2015&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In his introduction, guest editor Andrew McCarthy says that the best travel writing is “the anonymous and solitary traveler capturing a moment in time and place, giving meaning to his or her travels.” The stories in The Best American Travel Writing 2015 demonstrate just that spirit, whether it is the story of a marine returning to Iraq a decade after his deployment, a writer retracing the footsteps of humanity as it spread from Africa throughout the world, or looking for love on a physics-themed cruise down the Rhone River. No matter what the subject, the writers featured in this volume boldly call out, “Yes, this matters. Follow me!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781634502368&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Almost_Anywhere.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Almost Anywhere: Road Trip Ruminations on Love, Nature, National Parks, and Nonsense&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Krista Schlyer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781634502368&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Almost-Anywhere-Ruminations-National-Nonsense/dp/1634502361&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/902657330&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24693936-almost-anywhere&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At twenty-eight years old, Krista Schlyer sold almost everything she owned and packed the rest of it in a station wagon bound for the American wild. Her two best friends joined her—one a grumpy, grieving introvert, the other a feisty dog—and together they sought out every national park, historic site, forest, and wilderness they could get to before their money ran out or their minds gave in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781619025677&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Boundless.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Boundless: Tracing Land and Dream in a New Northwest Passage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kathleen Winter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781619025677&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Boundless-Tracing-Dream-Northwest-Passage/dp/1619025671&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/903424563&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20662570-boundless&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2010, bestselling author Kathleen Winter (Annabel) embarked on a journey across the storied Northwest Passage, among marine scientists, historians, archaeologists, anthropologists, and curious passengers. From Greenland to Baffin Island and all along the passage, Winter bears witness to the new math of the North—where polar bears mates with grizzlies, creating a new hybrid species; where the earth is on the cusp of yielding so much buried treasure that five nations stand poised to claim sovereignty of the land; and where the local Inuit population struggles to navigate the tension between taking part in the new global economy and defending their traditional way of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608867370&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Lumberjanes_vol2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lumberjanes Vol. 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Noelle Stevenson, Grace Ellis, Shannon Watters, and Brooke Allen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608867370&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Lumberjanes-Vol-2-Noelle-Stevenson/dp/1608867374&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/903510944&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24886016-lumberjanes-vol-2&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jo, April, Mal, Molly and Ripley are five best pals determined to have an awesome summer together…and they’re not gonna let any insane quest or an array of supernatural critters get in their way! But having stumbled onto a mysterious force wreaking havoc in the camp, it’s a race through the woods as the Lumberjanes work together to save not only their friends, but maybe even the whole world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781476727394&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Explorers_Guild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Explorers Guild, Volume 1: A Passage to Shambhala&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kevin Costner, Jon Baird, and Rick Ross&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781476727394&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Explorers-Guild-Passage-Shambhala/dp/1476727392&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/926879500&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25363511-the-explorers-guild&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Set against the backdrop of World War I, with Western Civilization on the edge of calamity, the first installment in The Explorers Guild series, A Passage to Shambhala, concerns the Guild’s quest to find the golden city of Buddhist myth. The search will take them from the Polar North to the Mongolian deserts, through the underground canals of Asia to deep inside the Himalayas, before the fabled city finally divulges its secrets and the globe-spanning journey plays out to its startling conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780765335296&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Radiance.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Radiance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Catherynne M. Valente&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780765335296&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Radiance-Novel-Catherynne-M-Valente/dp/0765335298&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908146174&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18490533-radiance&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Severin Unck’s father is a famous director of Gothic romances in an alternate 1986 in which talking movies are still a daring innovation due to the patent-hoarding Edison family. Rebelling against her father’s films of passion, intrigue, and spirits from beyond, Severin starts making documentaries, traveling through space and investigating the levitator cults of Neptune and the lawless saloons of Mars. For this is not our solar system, but one drawn from classic science fiction in which all the planets are inhabited and we travel through space on beautiful rockets. Severin is a realist in a fantastic universe.
But her latest film, which investigates the disappearance of a diving colony on a watery Venus populated by island-sized alien creatures, will be her last. Though her crew limps home to earth and her story is preserved by the colony’s last survivor, Severin will never return.
Told using techniques from reality TV, classic film, gossip magazines, and meta-fictional narrative, Radiance is a solar system-spanning story of love, exploration, family, loss, quantum physics, and silent film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780873519885&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Think_South.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Think South: How We Got Six Men and Forty Dogs Across Antarctica&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cathy de Moll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780873519885&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Think-South-Forty-Across-Antarctica/dp/0873519884&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/910980964&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25715251-think-south&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does it take to move forty dogs, three sleds, twenty tons of food and gear, and six men from all over the world across nearly four thousand of the coldest miles on earth? Cathy de Moll, the executive director of the 1990 International Trans-Antarctica Expedition, introduces the wild cast of characters who made it happen, on the ice and off: leaders Will Steger and Jean-Louis Etienne, who first met accidentally, on the way to the North Pole; Valery Skatchkov, the Soviet bureaucrat who supplied a “hot” Russian airplane; Yasue Okimoto, who couldn’t bear to leave headquarters in Minnesota while her boyfriend was on the ice; Qin Dahe, the Chinese member of the team, who didn’t know how to ski; the millions of children who followed the expedition in schools around the world, learning about the fragility and ferocity of the seventh continent; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780816698547&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Portage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Portage: A Family, a Canoe, and the Search for the Good Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Sue Leaf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780816698547&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Portage-Family-Canoe-Search-Good/dp/0816698546&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924212425&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25362771-portage&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When as a child she first saw a canoe gliding on Lake Alexander in central Minnesota, Sue Leaf was mesmerized. The enchantment stayed with her and shimmers throughout this book as we join Leaf and her family in canoeing the waterways of North America, always on the lookout for the good life amid the splendors and surprises of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/11/11/October_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/11/11/October_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>September Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every month tons of new adventure books are published. And every month I realize that I will never be able to actually read them all. But I wanted to provide a list of a few adventure books that were published last month that are definitely going on my to-be-read list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;September’s list, for some reason, is all non-fiction. That’s odd for me. Most of the books are also nature books, highlighting a facet of the natural world. One that I am especially excited about is the illustrated edition of Darwin’s &lt;em&gt;The Voyage of the Beagle&lt;/em&gt;. Well, that and Ferlinghetti’s &lt;em&gt;Writing Across the Landscape&lt;/em&gt;. I would expect to see at least one of those two reviewed here in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781631490019&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Writing_Across_the_Landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Writing Across the Landscape: Travel Journals 1960-2013&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Ferlinghetti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781631490019&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Across-Landscape-Journals-1960-2013/dp/163149001X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/902661510&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25622234-writing-across-the-landscape&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the course of an adventured-filled life, now in its tenth decade, Lawrence Ferlinghetti has been many things: a poet, painter, pacifist, publisher, courageous defender of free speech, and owner of San Francisco’s legendary City Lights bookstore. Now the man whose A Coney Island of the Mind became a generational classic reveals yet another facet of his manifold talents, presenting here his travel journals, spanning over sixty years. Selected from a vast trove of mostly unpublished, handwritten notebooks, and edited by Giada Diano and Matthew Gleeson, Writing Across the Landscape becomes a transformative work of social, cultural, and literary history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781583949603&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Ocean_Country.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ocean Country: One Woman’s Voyage from Peril to Hope in her Quest To Save the Seas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Liz Cunningham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781583949603&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Ocean-Country-Womans-Voyage-Peril/dp/1583949607&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/898228420&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25852915-ocean-country&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ocean Country&lt;/em&gt; is an adventure story, a call to action, and a poetic meditation on the state of the seas. But most importantly it is the story of finding true hope in the midst of one of the greatest crises to face humankind, the rapidly degrading state of our environment. After a near-drowning accident in which she was temporarily paralyzed, Liz Cunningham crisscrosses the globe in an effort to understand the threats to our dazzling but endangered oceans. This intimate account charts her thrilling journey through unexpected encounters with conservationists, fishermen, sea nomads, and scientists in the Mediterranean, Sulawesi, the Turks and Caicos Islands, and Papua, New Guinea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385350662&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Invention_of_Nature.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Invention of Nature: Alexander von Humboldt’s New World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Andrea Wulf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385350662&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Invention-Nature-Alexander-Humboldts/dp/038535066X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/911240481&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23995249-the-invention-of-nature&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alexander von Humboldt (1769–1859) was an intrepid explorer and the most famous scientist of his age. In North America, his name still graces four counties, thirteen towns, a river, parks, bays, lakes, and mountains. His restless life was packed with adventure and discovery, whether he was climbing the highest volcanoes in the world or racing through anthrax-infected Siberia or translating his research into bestselling publications that changed science and thinking. Among Humboldt’s most revolutionary ideas was a radical vision of nature, that it is a complex and interconnected global force that does not exist for the use of humankind alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781571313454&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Of_Bonobos_and_Men.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Of Bonobos and Men: A Journey to the Heart of the Congo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Deni Béchard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781571313454&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Bonobos-Men-Journey-Heart-Congo/dp/1571313451&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/921935166&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25074323-of-bonobos-and-men&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bonobos have captured the public imagination in recent years, due not least to their famously active sex lives. Less well known is the fact that these great apes don’t kill their own kind, and that they share nearly 99% of our DNA. Their approach to building peaceful coalitions and sharing resources has much to teach us, particularly at a time when our violent ways have pushed them to the brink of extinction. Animated by a desire to understand bonobos and learn how to save them, acclaimed author Deni Ellis Béchard traveled into the Congo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544323520&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Deep_South.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Deep South: Four Seasons on Back Roads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Paul Theroux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544323520&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Deep-South-Four-Seasons-Roads/dp/0544323521&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/904755965&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719344-deep-south&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paul Theroux has spent fifty years crossing the globe, adventuring in the exotic, seeking the rich history and folklore of the far away. Now, for the first time, in his tenth travel book, Theroux explores a piece of America theDeep South. He finds there a paradoxical place, full of incomparable music, unparalleled cuisine, and yet also some of the nation’s worst schools, housing, and unemployment rates. It’s these parts of the South, so often ignored, that have caught Theroux’s keen traveler’s eye.On road trips spanning four seasons, wending along rural highways, Theroux visits gun shows and small-town churches, laborers in Arkansas, and parts of Mississippi where they still call the farm up the road the plantation. He talks to mayors and social workers, writers and reverends, the working poor and farming families the unsung heroes of the south, the people who, despite it all, never left, and also those who returned home to rebuild a place they could never live without. From the writer whose great mission has always been to transport us beyond that reading chair, to challenge himself and thus, to challenge us (“Boston Globe”), “Deep South “is an ode toa region, vivid and haunting, full of life and loss alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780760348130&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Voyage_of_the_Beagle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Voyage of the Beagle: The Illustrated Edition of Charles Darwin’s Travel Memoir and Field Journal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Charles Darwin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780760348130&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Voyage-Beagle-Illustrated-Edition/dp/0760348138&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905450218&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24396919-the-voyage-of-the-beagle&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This volume is the first fully illustrated edition of Darwin’s journal and includes excerpts of &lt;em&gt;On the Origin of Species&lt;/em&gt; so the reader can connect the author’s journey with his discovery that made him famous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/10/07/September_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/10/07/September_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lumberjanes Vol. 1, Beware the Kitten Holy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608866878&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Lumberjanes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;Lumberjanes Vol. 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I wish that there was actually a place called Miss Quinzella Thiskwin Penniquiqul Thistle Crumpet’s Camp for Hardcore Lady-Types. I really do. I would drop everything and go there right now to spend the rest of my days earning Lumberjane badges and having adventures with the best friends that I would surely meet there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lumberjanes Vol. 1, Beware the Kitten Holy&lt;/em&gt;, collects the first four issues of the Lumberjanes comic, written by Noelle Stevenson and Grace Ellis, created by Shannon Watters, Grace Ellis, and Noelle Stevenson, and illustrated by Brooke Allen. The story follows five friends—Mal, Molly, Jo, Ripley, and April—as they battle three-eyed foxes, explore a mysterious cave, and deal with yetis, all while staying true to the Lumberjane motto: “Friendship to the Max!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of book that I wish there were more of. Because I want to read them and, mostly, because I want to give them to my daughter to read. She’s six and I would love for her to have more books that show girls having fun adventures and kicking butt and being smart. I want her to have more books about girls in which being a girl isn’t the defining factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, for me, is one of the wonderful things about this book. Yes, the characters are all girls. Yes, they are at a camp for “hardcore lady-types.” But foremost, and above all that, they are people. The fact that they are female people doesn’t define what they think they can or cannot do. Each character has her own style and interests and each character is loved and valued for who she is as an individual. I really, really want more books, especially books for kids, that do this. And not just for girls. For everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most wonderful thing about this book, however, is that it is just plain fun to read. It’s listed for fifth grade and up, but I loved it every bit as much as my six-year-old. The illustrations are fantastic, the stories are fun, and the characters leaped right off the page and into my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Lumberjanes-Vol-2-Noelle-Stevenson/dp/1608867374&quot;&gt;Volume two&lt;/a&gt; is due out in October and I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html</guid>
        
        <category>graphic</category>
        
        <category>novel,</category>
        
        <category>comic</category>
        
        <category>book,</category>
        
        <category>middle-grade,</category>
        
        <category>girls</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Oregon Trail: A New American Journey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781451659160&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Oregon_Trail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;The Oregon Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May of 2011, Rinker Buck, his brother Nick, and Nick’s dog Olive Oyl set off in a covered wagon hitched to a three-mule team to cross the Oregon Trail. Buck, driven by what he calls “crazyass passion” and a romantic memory of a childhood trip he took with his father and siblings across Pennsylvania in a covered wagon, conceived of the trip almost on a whim. “Only a delusional jackass, or someone seriously off his medications, would pull off the road at the Hollenberg Ranch one fine summer afternoon and concoct such a preposterous scheme,” he writes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But you can’t save an addictive dreamer from himself, and that jackass happens to be me. Already, powerful forces were drawing me west. I felt an irresistible urge to forsake my life back east for a rapturous journey across the plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinker is clearly a romantic and throughout the book he walks a fine line between romanticism and reality. In fact, this duality informs much of the book. Even as Rinker is drawn to a romantic vision of the trail, waxing poetic about life in the wagon and how he never wants the trip to end, he complicates that vision of the trail with historical fact and his own experience. Whether discussing the trail itself, the relationships between the pioneers and the native tribes, the history of mule breeding, or even the genesis of the word “pioneer,” nothing is as simple as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping to tip the scales more towards the reality end of the spectrum is Rinker’s brother Nick. Nick is a consummate tinkerer and free spirit, the opposite of Rinker in many ways. “I am bookish and neat,” Rinker writes, “with a fondness for antique furniture, good wine, and clean cars. If I am depressed or have writer’s block, I spend the afternoon logging in the woods or ironing my Brooks Brothers shirts. Nick buys a new Carhartt shirt at Reny’s Discount in Damariscotta and breaks it in by using it as an oil rag on the way home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the relationship between the two brothers deepen as they learn to appreciate each other is one of the most enjoyable parts of the book. While Rinker has a tendency to brood and struggle with the differences between simple ideals and the complications of reality, Nick, however, has no such compunctions. “There’s no fuckin cure for any of us, Rinker,” Nick tells his brother. “Get into it dickhead. I’m fucked up, you’re fucked up, okay? Fucked up is normal.” And while Rinker both dreams up and plans out the trip, examining maps and historical records of the trail, Nick, with his encyclopedic knowledge of the workings of wagons and mules, quickly proves himself an ideal, if not essential, trail companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brothers together face the many challenges inherent in traveling the trail and it doesn’t take long for them to figure out what every adventurer figures out eventually. “This is just a whole lot of work,” Nick puts it succinctly on the first afternoon. Hitching the mules, a dangerous and nerve-wracking undertaking on the best of days; staying awake in the driver’s seat so as not to fall and get crushed under the wagon wheels; finding clean water and places to camp; bathing, feeding, watering, and generally caring for the mules; figuring out the best route—all of this is hard work they must deal with on a daily basis. On top of that are stretches of challenging terrain, nasty weather, and bridges that spook the mules, among many other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it also doesn’t take long for them to learn another lesson that every adventurer also eventually learns: no one does any of this alone. The Buck brothers find that along the trail, hardly a day goes by when someone doesn’t offer help in some way. Ranchers show them the best places to camp and give them advice on the route they should take; trail historians pass along valuable information both about the historical trail and its current condition; kids come out to feed apples to the mules and play with Olive Oyl; people take them in, offering them meals and showers and all sorts of kindnesses. The acknowledgements section at the end reads like its own chapter and is well worth looking through, if for no other reason than to appreciate the generosity offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something about pushing yourself to accomplish a feat most people would write off as insane that can make you feel alive in ways you never knew possible. Facing the insurmountable, making mistake after mistake after mistake, and loving every minute of it—this is adventure. “The wrong outcome, or no outcome at all, is often the only result of a journey,” Rinker writes, reflecting on what his journey meant in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The impossible is doable as long as you have a great brother and good trail friends. Uncertainty is all. Crazyass passion is the staple of life and persistence its nourishing force. Without them, you cannot cross the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/08/18/Oregon_Trail.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/08/18/Oregon_Trail.html</guid>
        
        <category>travelogue,</category>
        
        <category>U.S.,</category>
        
        <category>non-fiction,</category>
        
        <category>adult</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
