<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Edge of Uncertainty</title>
    <description>Reviews of Adventure Books
</description>
    <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 19:18:17 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 19:18:17 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>October Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every month tons of new adventure books are published. And every month I realize that I will never be able to actually read them all. But I wanted to provide a list of a few adventure books that were published last month that look interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month I have some fiction! Well, three fiction books out of eight. But one of them is Volume Two of &lt;em&gt;Lumberjanes&lt;/em&gt; (I reviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html&quot;&gt;Volume 1&lt;/a&gt; in September) and that ought to count for something. More than something. I’ve already read it. It’s amazing. You should pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the other books that came out in October, I think I’m most excited about &lt;em&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Radiance&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/em&gt; has essays from some amazing writers I’ve read before (Paul Theroux, Maud Newton, Gary Schteyngart) and some that I’m sure are equally amazing, but that I just haven’t come across yet. &lt;em&gt;Radiance&lt;/em&gt; just looks incredible. It’s described as “a decopunk pulp SF alt-history space opera mystery” and I don’t even know what that means, but I want to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544569645&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Best_American_Travel_Writing_15.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Best American Travel Writing 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edited by Andrew McCarthy and Jason Wilson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544569645&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Best-American-Travel-Writing-2015/dp/0544569644&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/922687833&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719269-the-best-american-travel-writing-2015&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In his introduction, guest editor Andrew McCarthy says that the best travel writing is “the anonymous and solitary traveler capturing a moment in time and place, giving meaning to his or her travels.” The stories in The Best American Travel Writing 2015 demonstrate just that spirit, whether it is the story of a marine returning to Iraq a decade after his deployment, a writer retracing the footsteps of humanity as it spread from Africa throughout the world, or looking for love on a physics-themed cruise down the Rhone River. No matter what the subject, the writers featured in this volume boldly call out, “Yes, this matters. Follow me!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781634502368&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Almost_Anywhere.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Almost Anywhere: Road Trip Ruminations on Love, Nature, National Parks, and Nonsense&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Krista Schlyer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781634502368&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Almost-Anywhere-Ruminations-National-Nonsense/dp/1634502361&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/902657330&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24693936-almost-anywhere&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At twenty-eight years old, Krista Schlyer sold almost everything she owned and packed the rest of it in a station wagon bound for the American wild. Her two best friends joined her—one a grumpy, grieving introvert, the other a feisty dog—and together they sought out every national park, historic site, forest, and wilderness they could get to before their money ran out or their minds gave in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781619025677&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Boundless.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Boundless: Tracing Land and Dream in a New Northwest Passage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kathleen Winter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781619025677&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Boundless-Tracing-Dream-Northwest-Passage/dp/1619025671&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/903424563&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20662570-boundless&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In 2010, bestselling author Kathleen Winter (Annabel) embarked on a journey across the storied Northwest Passage, among marine scientists, historians, archaeologists, anthropologists, and curious passengers. From Greenland to Baffin Island and all along the passage, Winter bears witness to the new math of the North—where polar bears mates with grizzlies, creating a new hybrid species; where the earth is on the cusp of yielding so much buried treasure that five nations stand poised to claim sovereignty of the land; and where the local Inuit population struggles to navigate the tension between taking part in the new global economy and defending their traditional way of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608867370&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Lumberjanes_vol2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Lumberjanes Vol. 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Noelle Stevenson, Grace Ellis, Shannon Watters, and Brooke Allen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608867370&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Lumberjanes-Vol-2-Noelle-Stevenson/dp/1608867374&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/903510944&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24886016-lumberjanes-vol-2&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jo, April, Mal, Molly and Ripley are five best pals determined to have an awesome summer together…and they’re not gonna let any insane quest or an array of supernatural critters get in their way! But having stumbled onto a mysterious force wreaking havoc in the camp, it’s a race through the woods as the Lumberjanes work together to save not only their friends, but maybe even the whole world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781476727394&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Explorers_Guild.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Explorers Guild, Volume 1: A Passage to Shambhala&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Kevin Costner, Jon Baird, and Rick Ross&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781476727394&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Explorers-Guild-Passage-Shambhala/dp/1476727392&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/926879500&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25363511-the-explorers-guild&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Set against the backdrop of World War I, with Western Civilization on the edge of calamity, the first installment in The Explorers Guild series, A Passage to Shambhala, concerns the Guild’s quest to find the golden city of Buddhist myth. The search will take them from the Polar North to the Mongolian deserts, through the underground canals of Asia to deep inside the Himalayas, before the fabled city finally divulges its secrets and the globe-spanning journey plays out to its startling conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780765335296&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Radiance.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Radiance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Catherynne M. Valente&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780765335296&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Radiance-Novel-Catherynne-M-Valente/dp/0765335298&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/908146174&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18490533-radiance&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Severin Unck’s father is a famous director of Gothic romances in an alternate 1986 in which talking movies are still a daring innovation due to the patent-hoarding Edison family. Rebelling against her father’s films of passion, intrigue, and spirits from beyond, Severin starts making documentaries, traveling through space and investigating the levitator cults of Neptune and the lawless saloons of Mars. For this is not our solar system, but one drawn from classic science fiction in which all the planets are inhabited and we travel through space on beautiful rockets. Severin is a realist in a fantastic universe.
But her latest film, which investigates the disappearance of a diving colony on a watery Venus populated by island-sized alien creatures, will be her last. Though her crew limps home to earth and her story is preserved by the colony’s last survivor, Severin will never return.
Told using techniques from reality TV, classic film, gossip magazines, and meta-fictional narrative, Radiance is a solar system-spanning story of love, exploration, family, loss, quantum physics, and silent film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780873519885&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Think_South.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Think South: How We Got Six Men and Forty Dogs Across Antarctica&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Cathy de Moll&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780873519885&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Think-South-Forty-Across-Antarctica/dp/0873519884&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/910980964&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25715251-think-south&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does it take to move forty dogs, three sleds, twenty tons of food and gear, and six men from all over the world across nearly four thousand of the coldest miles on earth? Cathy de Moll, the executive director of the 1990 International Trans-Antarctica Expedition, introduces the wild cast of characters who made it happen, on the ice and off: leaders Will Steger and Jean-Louis Etienne, who first met accidentally, on the way to the North Pole; Valery Skatchkov, the Soviet bureaucrat who supplied a “hot” Russian airplane; Yasue Okimoto, who couldn’t bear to leave headquarters in Minnesota while her boyfriend was on the ice; Qin Dahe, the Chinese member of the team, who didn’t know how to ski; the millions of children who followed the expedition in schools around the world, learning about the fragility and ferocity of the seventh continent; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780816698547&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/October15/Portage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Portage: A Family, a Canoe, and the Search for the Good Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Sue Leaf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780816698547&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Portage-Family-Canoe-Search-Good/dp/0816698546&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924212425&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25362771-portage&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When as a child she first saw a canoe gliding on Lake Alexander in central Minnesota, Sue Leaf was mesmerized. The enchantment stayed with her and shimmers throughout this book as we join Leaf and her family in canoeing the waterways of North America, always on the lookout for the good life amid the splendors and surprises of the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/11/11/October_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/11/11/October_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>September Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every month tons of new adventure books are published. And every month I realize that I will never be able to actually read them all. But I wanted to provide a list of a few adventure books that were published last month that are definitely going on my to-be-read list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;September’s list, for some reason, is all non-fiction. That’s odd for me. Most of the books are also nature books, highlighting a facet of the natural world. One that I am especially excited about is the illustrated edition of Darwin’s &lt;em&gt;The Voyage of the Beagle&lt;/em&gt;. Well, that and Ferlinghetti’s &lt;em&gt;Writing Across the Landscape&lt;/em&gt;. I would expect to see at least one of those two reviewed here in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781631490019&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Writing_Across_the_Landscape.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Writing Across the Landscape: Travel Journals 1960-2013&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Lawrence Ferlinghetti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781631490019&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Writing-Across-Landscape-Journals-1960-2013/dp/163149001X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/902661510&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25622234-writing-across-the-landscape&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over the course of an adventured-filled life, now in its tenth decade, Lawrence Ferlinghetti has been many things: a poet, painter, pacifist, publisher, courageous defender of free speech, and owner of San Francisco’s legendary City Lights bookstore. Now the man whose A Coney Island of the Mind became a generational classic reveals yet another facet of his manifold talents, presenting here his travel journals, spanning over sixty years. Selected from a vast trove of mostly unpublished, handwritten notebooks, and edited by Giada Diano and Matthew Gleeson, Writing Across the Landscape becomes a transformative work of social, cultural, and literary history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781583949603&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Ocean_Country.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Ocean Country: One Woman’s Voyage from Peril to Hope in her Quest To Save the Seas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Liz Cunningham&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781583949603&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Ocean-Country-Womans-Voyage-Peril/dp/1583949607&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/898228420&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25852915-ocean-country&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ocean Country&lt;/em&gt; is an adventure story, a call to action, and a poetic meditation on the state of the seas. But most importantly it is the story of finding true hope in the midst of one of the greatest crises to face humankind, the rapidly degrading state of our environment. After a near-drowning accident in which she was temporarily paralyzed, Liz Cunningham crisscrosses the globe in an effort to understand the threats to our dazzling but endangered oceans. This intimate account charts her thrilling journey through unexpected encounters with conservationists, fishermen, sea nomads, and scientists in the Mediterranean, Sulawesi, the Turks and Caicos Islands, and Papua, New Guinea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385350662&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Invention_of_Nature.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Invention of Nature: Alexander von Humboldt’s New World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Andrea Wulf&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780385350662&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Invention-Nature-Alexander-Humboldts/dp/038535066X&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/911240481&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23995249-the-invention-of-nature&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alexander von Humboldt (1769–1859) was an intrepid explorer and the most famous scientist of his age. In North America, his name still graces four counties, thirteen towns, a river, parks, bays, lakes, and mountains. His restless life was packed with adventure and discovery, whether he was climbing the highest volcanoes in the world or racing through anthrax-infected Siberia or translating his research into bestselling publications that changed science and thinking. Among Humboldt’s most revolutionary ideas was a radical vision of nature, that it is a complex and interconnected global force that does not exist for the use of humankind alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781571313454&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Of_Bonobos_and_Men.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Of Bonobos and Men: A Journey to the Heart of the Congo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Deni Béchard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781571313454&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Bonobos-Men-Journey-Heart-Congo/dp/1571313451&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/921935166&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25074323-of-bonobos-and-men&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bonobos have captured the public imagination in recent years, due not least to their famously active sex lives. Less well known is the fact that these great apes don’t kill their own kind, and that they share nearly 99% of our DNA. Their approach to building peaceful coalitions and sharing resources has much to teach us, particularly at a time when our violent ways have pushed them to the brink of extinction. Animated by a desire to understand bonobos and learn how to save them, acclaimed author Deni Ellis Béchard traveled into the Congo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544323520&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Deep_South.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Deep South: Four Seasons on Back Roads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Paul Theroux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780544323520&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Deep-South-Four-Seasons-Roads/dp/0544323521&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/904755965&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23719344-deep-south&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Paul Theroux has spent fifty years crossing the globe, adventuring in the exotic, seeking the rich history and folklore of the far away. Now, for the first time, in his tenth travel book, Theroux explores a piece of America theDeep South. He finds there a paradoxical place, full of incomparable music, unparalleled cuisine, and yet also some of the nation’s worst schools, housing, and unemployment rates. It’s these parts of the South, so often ignored, that have caught Theroux’s keen traveler’s eye.On road trips spanning four seasons, wending along rural highways, Theroux visits gun shows and small-town churches, laborers in Arkansas, and parts of Mississippi where they still call the farm up the road the plantation. He talks to mayors and social workers, writers and reverends, the working poor and farming families the unsung heroes of the south, the people who, despite it all, never left, and also those who returned home to rebuild a place they could never live without. From the writer whose great mission has always been to transport us beyond that reading chair, to challenge himself and thus, to challenge us (“Boston Globe”), “Deep South “is an ode toa region, vivid and haunting, full of life and loss alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780760348130&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Voyage_of_the_Beagle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The Voyage of the Beagle: The Illustrated Edition of Charles Darwin’s Travel Memoir and Field Journal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;by Charles Darwin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9780760348130&quot;&gt;Indiebound&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Voyage-Beagle-Illustrated-Edition/dp/0760348138&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905450218&quot;&gt;Library&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24396919-the-voyage-of-the-beagle&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This volume is the first fully illustrated edition of Darwin’s journal and includes excerpts of &lt;em&gt;On the Origin of Species&lt;/em&gt; so the reader can connect the author’s journey with his discovery that made him famous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/10/07/September_Books.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/10/07/September_Books.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lumberjanes Vol. 1, Beware the Kitten Holy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781608866878&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Lumberjanes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;Lumberjanes Vol. 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I wish that there was actually a place called Miss Quinzella Thiskwin Penniquiqul Thistle Crumpet’s Camp for Hardcore Lady-Types. I really do. I would drop everything and go there right now to spend the rest of my days earning Lumberjane badges and having adventures with the best friends that I would surely meet there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lumberjanes Vol. 1, Beware the Kitten Holy&lt;/em&gt;, collects the first four issues of the Lumberjanes comic, written by Noelle Stevenson and Grace Ellis, created by Shannon Watters, Grace Ellis, and Noelle Stevenson, and illustrated by Brooke Allen. The story follows five friends—Mal, Molly, Jo, Ripley, and April—as they battle three-eyed foxes, explore a mysterious cave, and deal with yetis, all while staying true to the Lumberjane motto: “Friendship to the Max!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of book that I wish there were more of. Because I want to read them and, mostly, because I want to give them to my daughter to read. She’s six and I would love for her to have more books that show girls having fun adventures and kicking butt and being smart. I want her to have more books about girls in which being a girl isn’t the defining factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, for me, is one of the wonderful things about this book. Yes, the characters are all girls. Yes, they are at a camp for “hardcore lady-types.” But foremost, and above all that, they are people. The fact that they are female people doesn’t define what they think they can or cannot do. Each character has her own style and interests and each character is loved and valued for who she is as an individual. I really, really want more books, especially books for kids, that do this. And not just for girls. For everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most wonderful thing about this book, however, is that it is just plain fun to read. It’s listed for fifth grade and up, but I loved it every bit as much as my six-year-old. The illustrations are fantastic, the stories are fun, and the characters leaped right off the page and into my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Lumberjanes-Vol-2-Noelle-Stevenson/dp/1608867374&quot;&gt;Volume two&lt;/a&gt; is due out in October and I can’t wait.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/09/08/Lumberjanes.html</guid>
        
        <category>graphic</category>
        
        <category>novel,</category>
        
        <category>comic</category>
        
        <category>book,</category>
        
        <category>middle-grade,</category>
        
        <category>girls</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Oregon Trail: A New American Journey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indiebound.org/book/9781451659160&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/books/Oregon_Trail.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bookcover&quot; title=&quot;The Oregon Trail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May of 2011, Rinker Buck, his brother Nick, and Nick’s dog Olive Oyl set off in a covered wagon hitched to a three-mule team to cross the Oregon Trail. Buck, driven by what he calls “crazyass passion” and a romantic memory of a childhood trip he took with his father and siblings across Pennsylvania in a covered wagon, conceived of the trip almost on a whim. “Only a delusional jackass, or someone seriously off his medications, would pull off the road at the Hollenberg Ranch one fine summer afternoon and concoct such a preposterous scheme,” he writes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But you can’t save an addictive dreamer from himself, and that jackass happens to be me. Already, powerful forces were drawing me west. I felt an irresistible urge to forsake my life back east for a rapturous journey across the plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rinker is clearly a romantic and throughout the book he walks a fine line between romanticism and reality. In fact, this duality informs much of the book. Even as Rinker is drawn to a romantic vision of the trail, waxing poetic about life in the wagon and how he never wants the trip to end, he complicates that vision of the trail with historical fact and his own experience. Whether discussing the trail itself, the relationships between the pioneers and the native tribes, the history of mule breeding, or even the genesis of the word “pioneer,” nothing is as simple as it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping to tip the scales more towards the reality end of the spectrum is Rinker’s brother Nick. Nick is a consummate tinkerer and free spirit, the opposite of Rinker in many ways. “I am bookish and neat,” Rinker writes, “with a fondness for antique furniture, good wine, and clean cars. If I am depressed or have writer’s block, I spend the afternoon logging in the woods or ironing my Brooks Brothers shirts. Nick buys a new Carhartt shirt at Reny’s Discount in Damariscotta and breaks it in by using it as an oil rag on the way home.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching the relationship between the two brothers deepen as they learn to appreciate each other is one of the most enjoyable parts of the book. While Rinker has a tendency to brood and struggle with the differences between simple ideals and the complications of reality, Nick, however, has no such compunctions. “There’s no fuckin cure for any of us, Rinker,” Nick tells his brother. “Get into it dickhead. I’m fucked up, you’re fucked up, okay? Fucked up is normal.” And while Rinker both dreams up and plans out the trip, examining maps and historical records of the trail, Nick, with his encyclopedic knowledge of the workings of wagons and mules, quickly proves himself an ideal, if not essential, trail companion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brothers together face the many challenges inherent in traveling the trail and it doesn’t take long for them to figure out what every adventurer figures out eventually. “This is just a whole lot of work,” Nick puts it succinctly on the first afternoon. Hitching the mules, a dangerous and nerve-wracking undertaking on the best of days; staying awake in the driver’s seat so as not to fall and get crushed under the wagon wheels; finding clean water and places to camp; bathing, feeding, watering, and generally caring for the mules; figuring out the best route—all of this is hard work they must deal with on a daily basis. On top of that are stretches of challenging terrain, nasty weather, and bridges that spook the mules, among many other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it also doesn’t take long for them to learn another lesson that every adventurer also eventually learns: no one does any of this alone. The Buck brothers find that along the trail, hardly a day goes by when someone doesn’t offer help in some way. Ranchers show them the best places to camp and give them advice on the route they should take; trail historians pass along valuable information both about the historical trail and its current condition; kids come out to feed apples to the mules and play with Olive Oyl; people take them in, offering them meals and showers and all sorts of kindnesses. The acknowledgements section at the end reads like its own chapter and is well worth looking through, if for no other reason than to appreciate the generosity offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something about pushing yourself to accomplish a feat most people would write off as insane that can make you feel alive in ways you never knew possible. Facing the insurmountable, making mistake after mistake after mistake, and loving every minute of it—this is adventure. “The wrong outcome, or no outcome at all, is often the only result of a journey,” Rinker writes, reflecting on what his journey meant in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The impossible is doable as long as you have a great brother and good trail friends. Uncertainty is all. Crazyass passion is the staple of life and persistence its nourishing force. Without them, you cannot cross the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/08/18/Oregon_Trail.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.edgeofuncertainty.com/2015/08/18/Oregon_Trail.html</guid>
        
        <category>travelogue,</category>
        
        <category>U.S.,</category>
        
        <category>non-fiction,</category>
        
        <category>adult</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
